A Finding Aid to the Richard Artschwager Papers, 1959-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.artsrich
Archives of American Art
Richard Artschwager papers
1959-2013
AAA.artsrich
Archives of American Art
5.5 Linear feet
The papers of Richard Artschwager measure 5.5 linear feet and date from 1959-2013. The collection documents Artschwager's activities as a sculptor and painter through extensive correspondence, subject files, talks and a lecture, exhibition files, printed material, and photographs.
Artschwager, Richard, 1923-
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, circa 1970-2013 (Boxes 1-3; 3.0 linear feet)
Series 2: Talks and Lecture, 1985-2009 (Box 4; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1976-2007 (Boxes 4-5; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1960-1994 (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1959-2012 (Boxes 5-6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1973, 2007 (OV 7; 0.1 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Richard Artschwager (1923-2013) lived and worked in New York City and Hudson, New York and was known primarily for his paintings and sculptures. Artschwager was born in Washington, D.C. and grew up in New Mexico. As a youth, Artschwager showed a talent for drawing. He studied chemistry and mathematics at Cornell University. In 1944, Artschwager interrupted his studies to enlist in the U.S. Army. After the war, he returned to Cornell to complete his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1948. Encouraged by his first wife, Elfriede Wejmelka to develop his interest in art, Artschwager moved to New York to study at the Studio School of Amédée Ozenfant. His paintings and drawings from this period were featured in two group shows at the Terrain Gallery in 1957 and at the Art Directions Gallery on Madison Avenue in 1959, where they were recognized by Donald Judd.
In the 1950s, in order to support his family, Artschwager turned to designing and manufacturing modern furniture. His woodworking skills inspired him to create sculptures from utilitarian objects such as tables, chairs, and mirrors. He is best known for the use of building materials Celotex and Formica in his work and for inventing an abstract form he called "blps" reliefs, stencils or decals that were installed randomly in museum, gallery and public spaces. From the mid-1980s to late 1990s, Artschwager designed large scale projects, though he continued to incorporate everyday domestic objects in his sculptures and paintings.
In 1965, Artschwager was given his first one-man exhibition at the Castelli Gallery and he remained with the Gallery for thirty years. He was also represented by Mary Boone, David Nolan, and the Gagosian Gallery. In the 1980s, Artschwager served on the Visual Arts Policy Committee at the National Endowment of the Arts. He was elected to the American Academy of Arts in 1992. He was a visiting artist at New Mexico State University, Soka University, Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, and the University of Arizona. Artschwager's work was the subject of a major surveys, including the Kunstmuseum Winterthur, Neues Museum, and Serpentine Gallery. He participated in numerous international group shows including the Venice Biennale and Documenta in Kassel, Germany. The Whitney Museum of American Art honored Artschwager with two travelling retrospective exhibitions in 1988 and 2012. In late 2012, Artschwager had one-man shows at the Gagosian Gallery and David Nolan Gallery.
Richard Artschwager died at the age of 89 years in 2013. He is survived by his wife, Ann Sebring Artschwager and three children from previous marriages.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Richard Artschwager and his wife Ann Artschwager in 2013.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Richard Artschwager measure 5.5 linear feet and date from 1959-2013. The collection documents Artschwager's activities as a sculptor and painter through extensive correspondence, subject files, talks and a lecture, exhibition files, printed material, and photographs.
Artschwager's correspondence with museums, galleries, artists, art historians, academic institutions, and publishers is professional in nature and relates to the scheduling of exhibitions, the lending of artwork, speaking engagements, and teaching proposals. Frequent correspondents include Lawrence Alloway, Leo Castelli Gallery, Gagosian Gallery, Galerie Franck + Schulte, Herbert F. Johnson Museum, Ivan Karp, Museum Ludwig, Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, Ingrid Schaffner, and the Whitney Museum of American Art. Included are letters from fellow artists, including William Copley, Eric Fischl, Ray Johnson, Louise Lawler, Sol Lewitt, Ed Ruscha, John Waters, and Betty Woodman. Correspondence also includes queries from curators, students, and collectors seeking provenance and biographical-related information. Some letters are annotated or illustrated with sketches by Artschwager.
The collection includes talks and lecture by Richard Artschwager that were held at such venues as the University of Wisconsin, Madison, Skowhegan School of Painting & Sculpture, and the Carpenter Center of the Visual Arts, Harvard University. Included is a discussion by art critics, Michael Kimmelman and Peter Schjeldahl and artists, Alex Katz and Elizabeth Murray on contemporary art. Recordings are on 4 sound discs, 3 videocassettes, 1 videodisc, and 7 electronic discs. Subject files mainly document solo and group exhibitions in the United States and abroad from the 1990s-2000s. Exhibition files consist of scattered materials mostly relating to group shows.
Printed material includes invitations and announcements as well as posters, reproductions, and brochures, mostly related to Richard Artschwager's exhibitions. Newspaper and magazine clippings document exhibition openings and the critical reception of his work. Included are a few photographs, mainly used as reference, including images of Leo Castelli by Hans Namuth used by Artschwager in preparing for his portrait of Castelli.
Related Archival Materials note
Among the resources relating to Richard Artschwager in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Artschwager, March 3-28, 1972.
Alloway, Lawrence, 1926-1990; Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts.; Castelli, Leo; Copley, William Nelson, 1919-1996; Fischl, Eric, 1948-; Gagosian Gallery.; Galerie Franck + Schulte.; Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Karp, Ivan C., 1926-2012; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Kimmelman, Michael; Lawler, Louise; Leo Castelli Gallery; LeWitt, Sol, 1928-2007; Murray, Elizabeth, 1940-; Museum Ludwig.; Museum of Contemporary Art (Chicago, Ill.); Namuth, Hans; Neuendorf, Hans; Ruscha, Edward; Schaffner, Ingrid; Schjeldahl, Peter; Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture; University of Wisconsin.; Waters, John, 1946-; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Woodman, Betty, 1930-; Art critics; Art, Modern--20th century; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sketches; Transcripts; Video recordings
- Correspondence, circa 1970-2013; Series 1; 3 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Scope and Contents note
  This series documents Richard Artschwager's correspondence with museums, galleries, artists, art historians, academic institutions, collectors, and publishers. Subjects include the scheduling of exhibitions, loans, preparation of catalog essays; speaking engagements and teaching positions; Artschwager's participation in art-related events; and requests for reproduction rights, provenance and biographical information. Also included are letters by Artschwager that discuss his work and the work of other artists. Among the correspondents are Lawrence Alloway, Gagosian Gallery, Galerie Franck + Schulte, Galerie Neuendorf, Herbert F. Johnson Museum, Ivan Karp, Kunsthalle Basel, Leo Castelli Gallery, Mary Boone Gallery, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, Museum of Modern Art, Ingrid Schaffner, Dorothy and Herbert Vogel, and the Whitney Museum of American Art. Letters from artists include Bill Copley, Eric Fischl, Ray Johnson, Louise Lawler, Gerhard Mack, and Betty Woodman. Found are scattered letters from John Baldesarri, Damien Hirst, Dorothea Rockburne, Ed Ruscha, and Holly Solomon. Also included are a few letters illustrated by Artschwager. There are letters from Ann Sebring Artschwager acting on behalf of her husband.
  Many of the letters have attachments, e.g., curricula vitae and artist's statements; business related material, e.g., informational sheets, scattered price lists, receipts, consignments; layouts of exhibition space; and printed material including clippings, exhibition announcements and invitations, and reviews; and photographs of artwork. Some of the correspondence is in German.
  Arrangement note
  Letters are filed alphabetically by the personal or corporate name. Correspondence with individuals is generally filed according to the name of the organization with which they were associated.
  - A, 1972-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Alfonso Artiaco Gallery, 1996-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alveryd, Bo, 1987-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1994; 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Artschwager, Richard, 1972-circa 2007 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Artschwager, Richard - Loyalty Oath Incident, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Asheville Art Museum, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - B, circa 1974-2011 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Bartman/Chuck Close Project, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Baumgartner, Manfred, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Belot, Judin, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - C, 1976-2010 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Cabinet des Estampes, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carnegie Museum of Art, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Carrie Haddad Gallery, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Contemporary Arts Center, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Contemporary Art Museum, St. Louis, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cooper-Hewitt, National Design Museum, Smithsonian Institution, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cornell University, Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Curt Marcus Gallery, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - D, 1972-2008 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Donald Young Gallery, 1997-2000; 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - E, 1982-2006 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Elias Fine Art, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - F, 1974-2010 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Fisher Landau Center for Art, 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Frederick R. Weisman Art Foundation, 1997-2008 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - G, 1973-2011 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Galerie Christian Meyer and Renate Kainer, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Galerie Franck + Schulte, 1991-2000; undated (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Galerie Ghislaine Hussenot, 1986-1997 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Galerie Hauser & White, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Galerie Thomas Schulte, 1999-2011 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Georg Kargl, 2005; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grant Selwyn Fine Art, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - H, 1975-2010 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Haus Der Kunst, "Deep Storage", 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - I, 1974-2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Independent Curators, Inc., 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Institute of Contemporary Art, University of Pennsylvania, 1976; 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - J, 1975-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - K, 1973-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Katonah Museum of Art, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kunsthalle Wien, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - L, 1975-2010; undated (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - La Rochelle, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lehmann Maupin, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Leo Castelli, 1973-2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Leo Castelli, Floor Plans, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Leo Castelli, Accounting Inventory, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lincoln Center, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Locks Gallery, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - M, 1973-2009; undated (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, 1988-2008 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, San Diego, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Museum Ludwig, 1973-2010; undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1983-2008 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - N, 1973-1999 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Nationalgalerie Berlin, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - O, 1988-2008 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Oetker/Schneider, 1998-2008 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - P, 1982-2008 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Parkett Publishers, undated; 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Paula Cooper Gallery, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Piece Unique, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Portikus Press, 1993-2000 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Prada, 2010-2013; undated; Includes 1 electronic disc: DVD (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Public Art Fund, Inc., 1991-2002 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - R, 1974-2011 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
  - Rolf Ricke, 1970-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rose Art Museum, 1999; 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - S, 1973-2011 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Schaffner, Ingrid, 1991-2010; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Skowhegan, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Smith College Museum, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Soka University of America, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - State University of New York, New Paltz, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stein, Judith, 2001; undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Susanne Hilberry Gallery, 1981-2010 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Swiss Graphic Society, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - T, 1977-2007 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tate Gallery, 1997-circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Toronto Book Fair, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - U, 1974-2006 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - University of Iowa School of Art, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - V, 1981-2010 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Voici, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - W, 1973-2010 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art/Castleberry, 1997-2009 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - X-Y, 1982-2007 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Xavier Hufkens, 1995-2007 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Yale School of Art, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Birthday and Holiday Cards, circa 1990-2011 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - First Names, circa 1970-2011 (Box 3, Folder 32-36)
  - Unidentified, 1984-2009; undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Loose Envelopes, 1994-2000; undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Talks and Lecture, 1985-2009; Series 2; 0.8 Linear feet Box 4
  This series includes talks and lectures held at such venues as the Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts, Harvard University, Museum of Modern Art, Skowhegan School of Painting & Sculpture, and the Museum of Contemporary Art in North Miami, Florida. Included is a panel discussion that was held in conjunction with a group exhibition featuring Richard Artschwager's work at the Bonnefantenmuseum in Maastricht, Netherlands; also included are the museum's interviews with the artists, including Artschwager, Steve Ginakos, Peter Saul, and John Tweedle.
  Talks by others consists of a panel discussion moderated by Judy Dobrzynski between art critics Michael Kimmelman and Peter Schjeldahl and artists Alex Katz and Elizabeth Murray. Recordings are on 4 sound discs, 3 videocassettes, 1 videodiscs, 5 electronic discs (CD), and 2 electronic discs (DVD).
  Talks and lectures are arranged in chronological order.
  - Talk at Madison, Wisconsin, 1985; 2 Sound discs (CD) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Talk, "Objecthood and Theatricality", 1999; Includes 1 sound disc (CD). (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Talk, "Beitrag, Richard Artschwager", 2001; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Talk, B. Magazin; "Richard Artschwager", 2003; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lecture, Skowhegan School, 2004; 2 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Talks, Three PowerPoint Presentations, 2004-2006; 3 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Talk, "Conversations with Contemporary Artists" series, Museum of Modern Art, 2006; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Panel Discussion and Interviews, "Exile on Main Street", 2009; 1 Videodiscs (DVD); 2 Electronic discs (DVD); 3 Videodiscs (DVD) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Talk by Others, "So Much Art, So Little Time: The Critics Role in the Art World", 2000; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Subject Files, 1976-2007; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  This series mostly contains files on Artschwager's exhibitions in the United States and Europe from the 1990s-2000s. Materials include biographical information, correspondence and memoranda, fact sheets, exhibition plans, checklists, sketches of layouts, contracts, loan agreements, cost estimates and receipts. Among the printed materials are press releases, exhibition catalogs, and photographs of exhibition installations. Also found are Artschwager's annotations on drafts of catalog essays.
  Recordings are on 1 videocassette and 2 sound cassettes. Additional materials related to Artschwager's exhibitions can also be found in Series 1: Correspondence and Series 4: Exhibition Files.
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Application Summary Sheets, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Arts Club of Chicago, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Brandeis University, Rose Art Museum -- "Time Boxes 2000", 1999-2000; Includes 1 videocassette (VHS) and 1 sound cassette. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Brooke Alexander, Multiples Show, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Centre Canadian d'Architecture, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cornell University, Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, 1993-2005 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Deutsche Bank, 2000-2007 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Documenta IX, Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Galerie Gisela Capitain/Nolan Eckman Gallery, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Krefelder Museum, 2003-2006 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Kunstmuseum Wintherthur, 1999-2006 (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
  - Kunstneres Hus, Images for Asmund Thorkildsen, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - MAK, 2000-2005; Includes 1 sound cassette. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Mary Boone Gallery, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Musee D'Art Moderne Et Contemporain De Strasbourg, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, 1997-2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Miami, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Museum Voor Moderne Kunst, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Neues Museum, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
  - Serpentine Gallery, 1999-2002 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Staatliche Graphische Saamlung, 2001-2003 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Staatliche Kunsthalle Baden-Baden, 1998-2000 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Exhibition Files, 1960-1994; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  This series contains scattered materials (photocopies) relating to Artschwager's group exhibitions. Letters, checklists, installation layouts, press releases, exhibition announcements, invitations, and posters are found in varying combinations. Included in the Leo Castelli file are price lists for the work of Artschwager and others.
  The files are arranged chronologically.
  - Group Shows, 1960-1994 (Box 5, Folder 18-25)
  - Group Shows, Leo Castelli, 1973-1991 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Printed Material, 1959-2012; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  Newspaper and magazine clippings consist of exhibition announcements and reviews of the artist's work. A list of citations records the reviews of Artschwager's early solo and group exhibitions, providing the name of the reviewer, publication, and date. Also found are exhibition invitations, posters, reproductions, and brochures. Some of the clippings are in German.
  Folders are arranged by format and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Invitations, 1991-2011; undated (Box 5, Folder 27-30)
  - Announcements, 1985-2012; undated (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Posters, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Reproductions, circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1965-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
  - Clippings, List of Citations, 1959-1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Brochures, 1987-2011 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Photographs, circa 1973; 2007; Series 6; 0.1 Linear feet OV 7
  Photographs include Hans Namuth's images that were used by Artschwager as source material for his portrait of Leo Castelli. An unidentified photograph presumably was also used for art reference.
  - Photographs, circa 1973; 2007 (Box OV 7)